Narrator: Part 2
William: I could picture the windmill I wanted to build,
but before I attempted something that big, I wanted to experiment with a small model first.
I found an empty plastic jar… .
Leaving the lid intact, I sawed off the bottom of the jar, then cut the sides into four large strips,
then fanned them out into blades.
I poked a hole through the centre of the lid and nailed it to one of the bamboo poles
my father was saving.... I planted the pole in the ground behind the kitchen.
But the wind hardly moved this contraption at all. The blades were too short. I needed extensions.
The floors in our bathhouses often fill with water so we install PVC pipes to serve as a drain.
Several years earlier, a bathhouse…collapsed, and they simply built another one beside it.
I knew there was a piece of pipe still buried under the bricks,
and after 20 minutes of digging around, I pulled it free.
I sawed off a long section, then cut it down the middle from top to bottom.
I stoked the fire in my mother’s kitchen, then held the pipe over the coals.
Soon it began to warp and blacken, becoming soft and easy to bend, like wet banana leaves.
Before the plastic could cool, I placed it on the ground and pressed it flat with a piece of iron sheet.
I then carved four blades with a saw, each one maybe 20 cm long.
I didn’t have a drill, so I had to make my own. First I heated a long nail in the fire,
then drove it through half a maize cob, creating a handle.
I placed the nail back on the coals until it became red hot,
then used it to bore holes into both sets of plastic blades. I then wired them together.
I didn’t have any pliers, so I used two bicycle spokes to bend and tighten the wires on the blades.
That’s when my mother arrived.
‘What are you doing messing in my kitchen?’ she said. ‘Get these toys out of here.’
I tried to explain about windmills and my plan to generate power,
but all she saw were some pieces of plastic stuck to a bamboo stick.
‘Go help your father in the fields,’ she said. …It was pointless to explain.
What I needed now was a bicycle dynamo or some kind of generator,
and I had no idea where I was going to find such a thing.